Guide to the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church records 2009.011
Brooklyn Historical Society
Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church records
1816-2011
1850-1990
Center for Brooklyn History
Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
2009.011
42.25 Linear Feet in 32 record cartons, six manuscript boxes, four flat boxes, and one small box
219 Megabytes in 1 digital file.
The records of the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church document the history of the church, from its founding in 1857 to 2011 (the collection includes material dating back 1816). These records include church bulletins, publications, scrapbooks, membership and vital records, financial records, annual reports, building and property records, clippings, and photographs. The files also document specific aspects of the church, including its pastors (especially Theodore L. Cuyler); the Session; its choir, organ, and music program; Elders and administrators; missionary work (in Korea, Kentucky, and locally in Brooklyn); its Christian education program; various church groups; and LAPC members' roles in World War I and World War II.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church, 2009. A second accrual of records was deposited at BHS by LAPC in September 2015.
Arrangement
The records are organized into 18 series:
Series 1: Church Bulletins
Series 2: Parish Newsletters
Series 3: Lafayette Record
Series 4: Scrapbooks
Series 5: Pastors
Series 6: Membership, marriage, and baptismal records
Series 7: Session, Board of Trustees, and financial records
Series 8: Church manuals and calendars
Series 9: Historical files
Series 10: Elders and Administrators
Series 11: Music and organ
Series 12: Building and property
Series 13: Mission work
Series 14: Sunday School
Series 15: Young People's Association
Series 16: War service records
Series 17: Clippings
Series 18: Photographs
Timeline
Timeline
1857 Park Presbyterian Church organized
1860 Rev. Theodore L. Cuyler becomes church pastor
1862 Lafayette Avenue church building completed and church's name is officially changed to the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church
1863 Cumberland Street Chapel organized by W.W. Wickes
1866 Prospect Park Chapel organized on Warren Street by William C. Mumford and other church members (soon thereafter it became the Memorial Presbyterian Church on 7th Avenue)
1867 Young People's Association established
1872 Rev. Cuyler invited Sarah Smiley, a Quaker preacher, to be the first woman ever to preach from a Presbyterian pulpit
1874 Olivet Chapel organized
1881 Dr. John Hyatt Brewer joins the church as its Musical Director
1884 The mission to Korea is established by church member Daniel W. McWilliams. Horace Grant Underwood leads the mission.
1886 Cuyler Chapel opened on Atlantic Avenue by the Young People's Association
1890 Rev. Cuyler retires in the 30th year of his pastorate
1890 Rev. David Gregg becomes the second pastor of the LAPC
1903 Rev. Gregg leaves the church to become president of Western Theological Seminary in Pittsburgh
1904 Rev. Cleland Boyd McAfee installed as third pastor of the LAPC
1907 Buckhorn Church organized in Kentucky by Rev. Harvey Murdoch
1908 First issue of the Lafayette Record published
1909 Rev. Cuyler passes away on Feburary 26th
1910 New church organ dedicated
1912 Rev. McAfee leaves the church to occupy the chair of Systematic Theology at the McCormick Seminary
1913 Rev. Charles Carroll Albertson becomes the fourth pastor of the LAPC
1917 Gregg Chapel organized by the Young People's Association on 4th Avennue. The chapel was established to serve the growing Italian immigrant population.
1919 Rev. Gregg passes away
1919 Parish House opens on property given to the church by John T. Underwood
1920 The Women's Federation was organized, uniting the Women's Home and Foreign Missionary Society, the Ladies' Benevolent Society, the Cuyler Mission Band, and the Lafayette Auxiliary of the Red Cross
1928 Rev. Albertson steps down as pastor
1930 Rev. Alvin E. Magary installed as fifth pastor of the LAPC
1931 Musical Director Dr. John Hyatt Brewer retires and passes away
1932 The steeple is removed from the church building due to safety concerns resulting from subway construction
1938 Rev. Magary marries church organist Marion Clayton
1944 Rev. McAfee passes away
1951 Women elected to the Session for the first time
1956 Women elected to the Board of Deacons for the first time
1956 Rev. Magary resigns as pastor
1957 Rev. George Litch Knight becomes the sixth pastor of the LAPC
1959 Rev. Albertson passes away
1964 Rev. Magary passes away
1989 Rev. Knight retires
1992 Rev. David W. Dyson is installed as the church's seventh pastor
1995 Rev. Knight passes away
2011 Rev. Dyson retires as church pastor
Historical note
The Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church (LAPC) was originally organized as the Park Presbyterian Church in the eleventh ward of Brooklyn, New York, in 1857. At first, the church was temporarily based in the former home of the Park Congregation Church on Carlton Avenue, near DeKalb Avenue, in what is today known as the Fort Greene neighborhood of Brooklyn.
In 1860, the church invited Rev. Theodore L. Cuyler to become its first pastor. Cuyler, a vocal supporter of the abolitionist movement, was then the pastor of the Market Street Dutch Reformed Church in New York City. Cuyler agreed to accept the call to Brooklyn on the condition that the church purchase land and erect a new church building on the corner of Lafayette Avenue and South Oxford Street. The congregation purchased the land just ten days later, and Cuyler was installed as pastor on April 24, 1860. The church building was completed and dedicated in March 1862, and the congregation was renamed the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church.
The congregation was greatly expanded under Cuyler, from 140 members in 1860 to over 2,300 in 1890. During this time period the church's Sabbath School was established, along with a number of church groups, such as the Young People's Associations, the Cuyler Mission Band, and Women's Home and Foreign Missionary Society. Several chapels were organized throughout Brooklyn, expanding the reach of the church beyond the Fort Greene neighborhood.
In 1872, Cuyler caused great controversy by inviting Sarah Smiley, a Quaker preacher, to be the first woman to deliver an address at a Presbyterian service.
Another major event which occurred during the Cuyler pastorate was the establishment of the Presbyterian mission in Korea, which was spearheaded by LAPC Elder Daniel W. McWilliams.
Cuyler retired in 1890 after serving 30 years as pastor for the LAPC. The congregation chose Rev. David Gregg, of the Park Street Congregational Church in Boston, as its second pastor. Gregg accepted the call and was installed on December 14, 1890. The church and its chapels continued to expand under his pastorate. Gregg remained at the church until 1903, when he accepted the call to be president of the Western Theological Seminary in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.
The third pastor of the LAPC, Rev. Cleland Boyd McAfee, was installed on October 8, 1904. He had previously served as pastor to the 41st Street Presbyterian Church in Chicago, Illinois. McAfee continued the church's support for missions, both locally and abroad, and was a strong proponent of the church's music program. A new organ was installed in November 1910. He resigned in June 1912, when he accepted the call to serve as the chair of Systematic Theology at McCormick Seminary in Chicago.
On May 6, 1913, Rev. Charles Carroll Albertson was installed as the fourth pastor of the LAPC. Albertson led the effort to enlarge the church's endowment fund during his fifteen year service as minister of the church. He was a leading advocate of the Social Gospel movement in American Protestantism. During his pastorate, the Buckhorn Association was established as a mission in rural Kentucky in 1916. Additionally, a Parish House was built in 1917 to house various community-service projects locally in Brooklyn. He retired on Easter Sunday, 1928.
Rev. Alvin E. Magary was installed as the fifth pastor of the LAPC on May 6, 1930. He led the church through a difficult period, as noted in the LAPC's One Hundredth Anniversary booklet, "with the depression, the war years and the confused times of the post-war period, Brooklyn changed in character far more than our immediate neighborhood. Older members of church families retired and moved away or were taken by death. Younger members of these families moved out of the neighborhood or city." Magary remained pastor for 26 years, retiring in 1956.
The sixth pastor of the LAPC, Rev. George Litch Knight, was installed on December 29, 1957. That year marked the 100th anniversary of the church. The congregation had shrunk dramatically in the previous years, from a height of 2,500 at the turn of the century to less than 100 in 1960. Knight guided the church through another period of change. He led the effort to rehabilitate the church building and oversaw the development of the church's Cultural Crossroads program in the 1970s. The church also catered to newly arrived ethnic populations, such as the "Spanish" congregation, led by Rev. Moises J. Senti, and the Korean congregation, led by Elder Chung H. Ro, Rev. John Y. Paik, and Rev. Sung Kook Shin.
Rev. Knight retired in 1989 after leading the church for over thirty years. He was succeeded by Rev. David W. Dyson, who was chosen as pastor in 1992. Dyson was ordained in 1972, and spent much of the 1970s and 1980s as a labor advocate, first for the United Farm Workers and then for the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union. Prior to coming to the LAPC, he served for two years as executive minister for the Riverside Church in Manhattan. He served as LAPC pastor for eighteen years, where his ministry focused on social justice, retiring in 2011.
As of October 2015, the LAPC is led by Interim Pastor Lindsay Borden.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access born digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org.
The majority of the materials in this collection are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org at least three weeks prior to research visit.
Scrapbooks in boxes 30-31 are brittle and flaking, so not available for research use.
Related archival materials at BHS
Presbyterian Churches of Brooklyn collection (ARC.241)
Religious organizations of Brooklyn collection (ARC.242)
American Board of Commissioners of Foreign Missions annual meeting book (1977.083)
Church Extension Board of the Presbytery of Brooklyn-Nassau records (1978.027)
Theodore L. Cuyler correspondence (1978.167)
Related archival materials at other repositories
Brooklyn Public Library holds a number of photographs relating to the LAPC.
Berea College Library's Southern Appalachian Archives holds two collections relating to the Buckhorn Association: the Buckhorn Children's Center Records (SAA 45) and the Buckhorn School Oral History Collection (SAA 94).
Scope and Contents
The records of the Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church document the history of the church, from its founding in 1857 to 2011 (the collection includes material dating back 1816). These records include church bulletins, publications, scrapbooks, membership and vital records, financial records, annual reports, building and property records, clippings, and photographs.
The files also document specific aspects of the church, including its pastors (especially Theodore L. Cuyler); the Session; its choir, organ, and music program; Elders and administrators; missionary work (in Korea, Kentucky, and locally in Brooklyn); its Christian education program; various church groups; and LAPC members' roles in World War I and World War II.
Newsletters; Kentucky |z Perry County; Church bulletins; Hymns; Missionaries |z Korea; Korea; Religious institutions |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; Missionaries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sermons; Typescripts; Manuscripts (document genre); Annual reports; Hymns |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Minutes; Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Clergy; Calendars; Presbyterians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Missions; Color slides; Photographs; Audiotapes; Presbyterian Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Programs (documents); Presbyterian church buildings |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x History; DVDs; Service books (religious texts); Videocassettes; Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Religious education of children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Baptismal registers; Marriage registers; American poetry |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Scrapbooks; Abolitionists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Recipes; Missionaries |z Kentucky |z Perry County; Church music |x Protestant churches |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Acetate film; Songbooks; Concert programs; Deeds; Death records; Temperance |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bible; Lincoln, Abraham; McAfee, Cleland Boyd; Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Gregg, David; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A. Presbytery of Buckhorn; Knight, George Litch; Lafayette Avenue Presbyterian Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Vassar College. Class of 1903; Third Reformed Presbyterian Church (New York, N.Y.); Moody, Dwight Lyman; Magary, Alvin E. (Alvin Edwin); Albertson, Charles Carroll; Underwood family; Cuyler, Theodore L. (Theodore Ledyard); Tiffany Glass & Decorating Company; Moore, Marianne; Hook & Hastings (Firm); Vamos, Jeffrey A.; Brooklyn City news; Dyson, David W.
- Series 1: Church Bulletins, 1882-2003; 10.5 Linear Feet in 11 record cartons
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Church Bulletins consist of weekly "orders of services" and notifications concerning upcoming events and organizational meetings held at the church and locally, new members, deaths, requests for donations to various charities, and other matters of interest to LAPC congregants. This series contains bulletins dating from 1882 to 2003. This not a complete collection of LAPC bulletins; there are many gaps in the series, especially for the years prior to 1930 and after 1990. Early bulletins which do not appear in this series are likely to be found in Series 4: Scrapbooks.
  Beginning in the 1970s, many of these announcements concern art exhibitions, music programs, and other cultural events held at LAPC. The series includes the programs, flyers, and other matter related to these events, including in the late 1970s and later, material regarding the performances, exhibitions, and other programs sponsored at LAPC by Cultural Crossroads, Inc.
  Included in this series are bulletins for special events, such as pastor installations and anniversaries, wedding and memorial services for church members, Children's Day, concerts, and building and organ dedications.
  Programs for concert and choir performances are especially well represented in the years 1882 to 1903.
  The series includes one folder of memorial service bulletins and programs dating from 1960 to 1976.
  Beginning in the mid-1970s, the series includes some parish newsletters which were filed with the church bulletins.
  - Church Bulletins (16 folders), 1882-1927 (Box 1, Folder 1-16)
  - Church Bulletins (17 folders), 1927-1935 (Box 2, Folder 1-17)
  - Church Bulletins (16 folders), 1935-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1-16)
  - Church Bulletins (16 folders), 1953-1963 (Box 4, Folder 1-16)
  - Church Bulletins (20 folders), 1963-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1-20)
  - Church Bulletins (14 folders), 1972-1979 (Box 6, Folder 1-14)
  - Church Bulletins (16 folders), 1980-1984 (Box 7, Folder 1-16)
  - Church Bulletins (15 folders), 1985-1990 (Box 8, Folder 1-15)
  - Church Bulletins (16 folders), 1991-1997 (Box 9, Folder 1-16)
  - Church Bulletins (15 folders), 1997-2001 (Box 10, Folder 1-15)
  - Church Bulletins (8 folders), 2002-2003 (Box 11, Folder 1-8)
- Series 2: Parish Newsletters, 1957-1991; 0.3 Linear Feet in five folders
  Series includes newsletters concerning parish activities and other matters of interest to the LAPC congregation.
  Prior to the date range of this series, this type of information was generally found in the Lafayette Record (Series 3).
  - Parish Newsletters (5 folders), 1957-1991 (Box 11, Folder 9-13)
- Series 3: Lafayette Record, 1907-1960, 1990-1991; 2.3 Linear Feet in two record cartons and eight folders
  The series contains issues of the Lafayette Record, LAPC's periodical that was published from 1907 to 1960, and then again in the early 1990s. The publication included sermons; announcements of births, deaths, and other personal events among the congregation; annual reports from the church's governing bodies; and information about activities from organizations affiliated with the church.
  - Lafayette Record (2 folders), 1907-1908 (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
  - Lafayette Record (21 folders), 1909-1928 (Box 12, Folder 1-21)
  - Lafayette Record (26 folders), 1929-1953 (Box 13, Folder 1-26)
  - Lafayette Record (6 folders), 1954-1960, 1990-1991 (Box 14, Folder 1-6)
- Series 4: Scrapbooks, 1858-1961; 5.25 Linear Feet in three record cartons, three manuscript boxes, and seven folders
  Arranged chronologically, with the centennial celebration scrapbook placed at the end of the series.
  The scrapbooks document the day-to-day affairs of the church, and include church bulletins, announcements, calendars, special event and concert programs, clippings, and other ephemera, dating from 1858 to 1961. LAPC organizations and affiliations, such as the Young People's Association, the Gregg Chapel, and the church bible school, are well represented in the scrapbooks.
  The series includes one scrapbook documenting the church's centennial celebration (1957).
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Scrapbooks in boxes 30-31 are brittle and flaking, so not available for research use.
  - 1858-1910 scrapbook (1-5 of 8 folders) (Box 30, Folder 1-5)
  - 1858-1910 scrapbook (6-8 of 8 folders) (Box 31, Folder 1-3)
  - 1910-1914 scrapbook (1-2 of 5 folders) (Box 31, Folder 4-5)
  - 1910-1914 scrapbook (3-5 of 5 folders) (Box 32, Folder 1-3)
  - 1914-1918 scrapbook (1-2 of 4 folders) (Box 32, Folder 4-5)
  - 1914-1918 scrapbook (3-4 of 4 folders) (Box 33, Folder 1-2)
  - 1918-1921 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
  - 1921-1925 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 18, Folder 5-8)
  - 1925-1929 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 18, Folder 9-12)
  - 1929-1932 scrapbook (1 of 4 folders) (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - 1929-1932 scrapbook (2-4 of 4 folders) (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - 1929-1932 scrapbook (3 folders) (Box 19, Folder 1-3)
  - Loose scrapbook pages, 1930s (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - 1932-1935 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 19, Folder 5-8)
  - 1935-1939 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 19, Folder 9-12)
  - 1939-1943 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 19, Folder 13-16)
  - 1943-1948 scrapbook (1 of 3 folders) (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - 1943-1948 scrapbook (2-3 of 3 folders) (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
  - 1948-1953 scrapbook (3 folders) (Box 20, Folder 3-5)
  - 1953-1957 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 20, Folder 6-9)
  - 1958-1960 scrapbook (3 folders) (Box 20, Folder 10-12)
  - 1960-1961 scrapbook (4 folders) (Box 21, Folder 1-4)
  - Centennial celebration scrapbook, 1957 (Box 33, Folder 6)
    General
    Oversize
- Series 5: Pastors, 1816-2011; 4.75 Linear Feet
  The series contains records relating to the church's first seven pastors (Cuyler, Gregg, McAfee, Albertson, Magary, Knight, and Dyson), and one interim pastor (Vamos).
  The series is organized into eight sub-series:
  Sub-series 5.1: Rev. Theodore L. Cuyler
  Sub-series 5.2: Rev. David Gregg
  Sub-series 5.3: Rev. Cleland B. McAfee
  Sub-series 5.4: Rev. Charles C. Albertson
  Sub-series 5.5: Rev. Alvin E. Magary
  Sub-series 5.6: Rev. George L. Knight
  Sub-series 5.7: Rev. Jeffrey A. Vamos (Interim Pastor)
  Sub-series 5.8: Rev. David W. Dyson
  - Sub-series 5.1: Rev. Theodore L. Cuyler, 1816-circa 1980s; 1 Linear Feet in one record carton
    The sub-series contains material related to Rev. Thedore L. Cuyler, most of which documents his time as pastor at the LAPC. It includes sermons (handwritten and published, 1852-1900s), correspondence (1854-1908), four bibles (1826-1890), portraits (circa 1850s-1900s), clippings (1867-1978), anniversary and retirement service programs (1885-1890), and published addresses delivered by Cuyler (1890-1896).
    Material related to his mother, wife, daughter, son, and grandson can also be found in the series. Addtionally, it contains some biographical materials related to Cuyler, as well as typescripts of a portion of his correspondence.
    There are several items of note in the series, including: an 1826 bible (in two volumes), presented to Culyer by his father; his mother's diary (1831-1834); an 1842 broadside advertising a temperance lecture delivered by Cuyler at the Canon Street Chapel (England); a collection of scrapbook pages which include poetry authored by Cuyler, abolitionist writings, and a list of his colleagues at Princeton University (1837-1842); and a handwritten sermon on Abraham Lincoln delivered shortly after his assasination (1865).
    The sub-series is organized into five sections:
    Section A: Bibles
    Section B: Sermons and writings
    Section C: Correspondence
    Section D: Portraits
    Section E: Other items
    Related Materials
    BHS holds an additional collection of Cuyler correspondence (1978.167)
    - Section A: Bibles, 1826-1890
      - Cuyler family bible (2 volumes), 1826 (Box 17, Folder 28-29)
      - Cuyler's bible, circa 1860s (Box 42, Folder 1)
      - Cuyler's bible, 1885 (Box 42, Folder 2)
      - Cuyler's bible, 1890 (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Section B: Sermons and other writings, 1837-circa 1900s
      - Scrapbook pages, 1837-1842 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        Collected while at Princeton. Includes poetry by Cuyler, abolitionist debates, and list of colleagues at Princeton.
      - Handwritten sermons, 1852-1901 (Box 17, Folder 2)
        Includes listings of where and when each sermon was delivered
      - The Empty Crib: A Book of Consolation advertisement, circa 1870s (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - "A Discourse on Abraham Lincoln" handwritten sermon and typescript, 1865 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Clippings - Sermons and talks, 1870s-1908 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - "Demas the Deserter" published sermon, 1884 (Box 17, Folder 6)
        The Pulpit Treasury vol. II no. 1; includes Cuyler portrait
      - Handwritten memorial to Mrs. Proal, circa 1890 (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Published addresses, 1890-1896 (Box 17, Folder 8)
        Lasell Seminary for Young Women (1890) and the Bible Society of Virgina (1896)
      - "A Shot at the Decanter" published sermon, circa 1900s (Box 17, Folder 9)
        First published in 1865
    - Section C: Correspondence, 1854-circa 1980s
      - Correspondence - To Cuyler, 1854-1891 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence - From Cuyler (originals), 1869-1908 (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence - From Cuyler (typescripts), circa 1980s (Box 17, Folder 12)
      - Letter from Edger Ketchum to Louise F. Cuyler, 1875 (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Letter to Mary Cuyler Cheesman regarding her mother, 1909 (Box 17, Folder 14)
        Incomplete
      - Theodore L. Cuyler Jr. letter from Kyoto, Japan, 1923 (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Section D: Portraits, circa 1850s-1920s
      - Lithographic portrait, signed by Cuyler, circa 1850s (Box 34, Folder -)